

# MIKE FISCHER

**CEO SUPERFOAM LTD** 



#### PROFILE —

Particularly enjoy driving change, developing solutions and am inspired by developing people and making a difference to businesses and society.

My career has followed a developmental / problem solving and entrepreneurial route. This has provided significant experience in multifaceted businesses requiring Turn Around skills, business optimization and change management solutions.

Strengths include a practical approach to challenges, applying a cool head with a team-based approach augmented by leadership skills, broad business experience, deep financial skills, strong analytical ability and a creative approach to problem solving.

A comfortable motivational communicator drawn from extensive experience gained during corporate responsibilities, lecturing and public presentations.



#### CONTACT -

ADDRESS Westlands, Nairobi, Kenya & Mooi

River 3300 South Africa

EMAIL mike.fischer@iafrica.com

**PHONE** +254 716 181 818



#### **SKILLS**





# EDUCATION

- MBA (Cum laude) // 2019
   BUSINESS SCHOOL NETHERLANDS
   Awarded a full academic scholarship
- CHARTERED ACCOUNTANT (S.A.) // 1986
   SOUTH AFRICAN INSTITUTE OF CHARTERED
   ACCOUNTANTS Membership 00145996
- POST GRADUATE DIPLOMA IN ACCOUNTING
   // 1983
   UNIVERSITY OF NATAL PIETERMARITZBURG
   KZN
- BCOM DEGREE // 1981
   UNIVERSITY OF NATAL PIETERMARITZBURG
   KZN
- S.A. NATIONAL DEFENSE FORCE // 1975 1976
   RANK WO2 / CANDIDATE OFFICER CITIZEN
   FORCE
- SCHOOLING AT TREVERTON COLLEGE PRIOR
   TO ESTCOURT HIGH SCHOOL MATRIC // 1974

# RECENT EXPERIENCE

 SUPERFOAM LTD - KENYA (NAIROBI) – (Turnaround)

STAFF SCALE - 450 // Sep 2016 - Present CEO - CHIEF EXECUTIVE OFFICER

Turnaround and change management challenge with overall responsibility for the organisation which manufactures foam and bedding products for supply to Kenyan clients.

My overall objectives include Strategic Planning, Brand development, Development of production efficiencies, Market Development and overall streamlining in order to maximize ROI.

Secured a Private Equity Investment to recapitalise and reposition the business into a regional East African structure.

CV – Mike Fischer 2018 Page 1 of 4

# HONEYDEW DAIRIES (PTY) LTD - SOUTH AFRICA - (Business Optimisation) STAFF SCALE - 800 // Oct 2012 - Aug 2016 COO - CHIEF OPERATING OFFICER

Agri Processing Factory producing commercial volumes of milk, cream, yoghurt, maas, juice and blends.

Responsibilities included the overall businesses optimization and development of production efficiencies, which were increased by 25%, as well as securing accreditation for the business in respect of FSA, HACCP and Export Accreditation in order to maximize the ROI.

Assisted with the sale of the business to a Farmers Co-Operative.

#### SEA KAY HOLDINGS LTD (LISTED ON THE JSE) – (Turnaround)

STAFF SCALE - 1000 // Mar 10 – Sep 2012 COO - CHIEF OPERATING OFFICER

Started with a business that was underfunded by R300m.

Devised and implemented the turnaround plan and implemented the change management strategy.

Unblocked and recovered R150m of old debt, redesigned the quality control process to ensure prompt certification and

payment for construction milestones.

Opened a new division in the province of KZN and devised a plan to recapitalize the business by buying a property to leverage access to finance.

Engaged with political leaders to secure bridging finance using the outstanding debt as collateral. Negotiated new contracts with Governmental agencies.

#### RAFFIA BAGS - KENYA (MOMBASA) – (Turnaround)

STAFF SCALE - 500 // July 2007 - March 2010 MD - MANAGING DIRECTOR

The task was to turnaround the business which specialized in the manufacture and distribution of polypropylene cement and agricultural bags to cement plants in East and Southern Africa.

Remedied operations by increasing un-utilised 50% capacity, resolved major quality problems to secure the major customer's continued support.

Grew the market substantially and successfully implemented a change management initiative.

#### FISCHER & ASSOCIATES – (Consulting)

// February 2010 – Present
International Investment Consultants and facilitators
specializing in minerals for India & Africa Initiatives

#### CLIFTON HILL NURSERY SCHOOL - HILLCREST – www.chns.co.za

// August 2015 – onwards OWNER (MY WIFE RUNS THE BUSINESS as an Investment for her future)

#### MARKET SECTOR EXPOSURE -

Corporate Governance	Mergers and Acquisitions
Business Development	Conflict resolution
Financial Director	Strategic Planning
Change management	Business Turnarounds and
	Business Optimization
Managing Director	Academic Lecturer
Book Author	Chief Operating Officer
Entrepreneur	Audit Professional

#### **CAREER ROLES**

Construction & Project	Property Development
management	
Project Development &	Manufacturing
Implementation	
Import & Distribution	Logistics
(Local & International)	
Management Consulting	Operations &maintenance
Turnaround Professional	Change Management
	Agent
University Academic	Government Contracts
(Skill Development)	

# PAST RESPONSIBILITIES

 ERNST & YOUNG (CA (S.A.) – DURBAN // 2005 - 2007 MANAGEMENT CONSULTANT TO TOYOTA

THATCHERS UNLIMITED - KZN REGION

 CONSTRUCTION - (Entrepreneurial)

 STAFF SCALE - 600 // 1998 - 2005
 CEO - CHIEF EXECUTIVE OFFI CER

Created the largest Thatch Roofing construction Business in KZN. Building contracts secured in KZN, Seychelles, Spain and also built many parts of the resorts for Ezemvelo (Giants Castle, Didima, Umfolozi).

Sold the business I wanted to re-entre professional life.

CV – Mike Fischer 2018 Page 2 of 4

#### TOWNHOUSE DEVELOPMENT DURBAN – (Entrepreneurial)

// 1997 - 1998

**CEO - CHIEF EXECUTIVE OFFICER** 

Designed and developed a up market property development in the Highway Area of KZN.

#### TOWN HOUSING – DURBAN

STAFF SCALE - 500 // 1994 - 1996
FINANCIAL DIRECTOR & PARTNER
Construction of GAP Housing and Commercial developments in Durban and Richards Bay.

#### WITNEY CHEMICALS – DURBAN – Financial Director

Importer and distributor of bulk chemicals used in the manufacture of paint and resin in South Africa.

Full responsibility of the financial functional and helped the MD develop a strategy to rationalise the business and sell it.

## DELOITTE (CA (S.A.) – DURBAN // 1988 - 1990 SENIOR MANAGEMENT CONSULTANT

Strategy planning development for the City of Durban, Transkei Government and Central Energy Fund.

#### UNIVERSITY OF NATAL & DURBAN WESTVILLE -DURBAN // 1984 - 1988

#### **LECTURER**

Accounting 1st, 2nd and 3rd year subjects as well as Management Accounting and Public Administration Accounting.

Co-authored a Book – Graded Questions in Financial Accounting – Wilson, Broome & Fischer.

#### • MANAGEMENT CONSULTANT – DURBAN

// 1985 – 1988

**CEO - CHIEF EXECUTIVE OFFICER** 

Implemented PC based Management Accounting Systems and customised software.

#### • FUTURE DISTRIBUTORS - DURBAN

STAFF SCALE - 200 // 1987-1988
FINANCIAL DIRECTOR – IMPORT &
DISTRIBUTION

Created a modeling agency a chain of Black Hairdressing salons and a wholesale Distribution organisation.

#### PRESSURE DIE CASTINGS – PIETERMARITZBURG

STAFF SCALE - 500 // 1983-1984 FINANCIAL CONTROLLER – MANUFACTURER  PIM GOLDBY (CA (S.A.) (NOW DELOITTE) -PIETERMARITZBURG

// 1981-1983

SENIOR AUDIT MANAGER WHILE SERVING ARTICLES AS PART OF CA (SA) TRAINING

# **VOLUNTARY / POSITIONS OF TRUST**

- BOARD MEMBER OF EZEMVELO KZN WILDLIFE STAFF SCALE - 1500 // Jan 2011 – March 2013 NOMINATED BY KWANALU
- BOARD MEMBER OF WESSA (WILDLIFE AND ENVIRONMENT SOCIETY OF SOUTH AFRICA // 2010 – 2014
- THOMAS MORE COLLEGE Chairman of the Board of Trustees
   950 - PUPILS // 1990 – 1998
   DURBAN CHAIRMAN OF BOARD / FINANCES
- CHAIRMAN OF THE GOVERNING BODY OF WINSTON PARK PRIMARY SCHOOL
   950 - PUPILS // 1989 – 1990

## **MEMBERSHIPS**

#### SAICA

SOUTH AFRICAN INSTITUTE OF CHARTERED ACCOUNTANTS — Membership 00145996

- In Progress CPA(K) (Local Credits of Company Law & Tax Law Pending)
- SARIPA (South African Restructuring and Insolvency Practitioners Association) – Application being Submitted

# SELECTED ACHIEVEMENTS —

#### IN FINANCE

- Turn around Raffia (Mombasa, Kenya)
- Turn around Witney losses to profit
- Restructure Above
- Negotiated sale of Company to Engen
- Yielded a significant profit on FOREX portfolio
- Managed finances of operations in RSA for USA based operations.
- Managed an aviation TAX scheme.
- Toyota Audit 2006 Inventory R5 Billion.

CV – Mike Fischer 2018 Page 3 of 4

Supervised Sarbains Oxley compliance - Toyota

#### **GENERAL MANAGEMENT**

- Growth of Agri Processing facility Honeydew Dairies
- Turnaround of Sea Kay Holding Ltd
- Managed and developed the growth of a private school -100 teachers & 950 pupils
- Managed and developed own construction operation max 600 staff / Subcontractors
- Managed and developed manufacturing operation in Kenya – 400 staff

#### **CONSULTANT**

- Developed policies and procedures for the Transkei Government as well the Training manuals & implementation program for above
- Conflict resolution
- Listing a company on the JSE DCM
- Computerized listed groups' stores in RSA
- **Turnaround Strategy** 
  - for Listed Construction Co. Sea Kay Ltd.
  - Raffia Bags (Kenya) Ltd
  - Superfoam Ltd (Kenya)

#### **ENTREPRENEUR**

- Developed Greenfield operations (Construction, Import / Distribution & Management Consultancy)
- Pioneered franchising of the thatching industry In KZN
- Property Developer
- Partner of a Wedding Venue
- Owner of a School in Hillcrest

#### **LEADERSHIP**

- MD of manufacturing organization Asset Base USD 25m.
- Developed and ran OWN construction business
- Developed and ran OWN property dev. business
- Chaired the Board of Trustees of private school
- Developed own management consultancy
- Chaired Community Ratepayers' Association
- WOII / Candidate Officer during military service
- Chaired the implementation of a proposed gated community initiative - Winston Park
- Chaired Board of Trustees of Thomas More College and grew it from 125 pupils to 970 over 8 years
- Conceptualized & Implemented "My Schools Credit Card"
- Treasurer of Underwater Club
- Chairman of the Gillitts Ratepayers Association

- Board Member of WESSA (Wildlife and Environment Society of SA)
- Board Member of Ezemvelo KZN Wildlife.



#### **PERSONAL**

- Married to Liz (42 years)
- Three Adult Children
- Family live on a farm in the KZN Midlands
- Hobbies and personal pursuits
  - Played First Team Rugby (Wing) and Swimming at School
  - Reading and current affairs
  - Horse Riding (Show Jumped while at School)
  - **Kite Boarding**
  - Wind Surfing (Sailed competitively and was sponsored by Fero Brake)
  - Water Skiing (Barefooting and Slalom)

  - Family Fun Days

#### NEXT CHALLANGES -

- Private Pilot's Licence
- Climb Kilimanjaro
- Complete registration with CPA(K)

CV - Mike Fischer 2018 Page 4 of 4